If you clone a human brain and then take
that brain and put it inside of an
animal, have you just cloned a human
being and created an animal with rights?
This is the question that's very
important right now and people are
trying to tackle it because the science
is moving much faster than the law. Let
me walk you through some of the most
controversial studies that have come out
and talk about why maybe we aren't going
to do them again. Yes, people have
concerns. Brain organoids are
essentially tiny versions of human
brains, and they can be transplanted
into a mouse's brain, and they can even
repair parts of the tissue and restore
function. They could even recover rats
from blankness when the visual cortex
was damaged. This kind of study has been
repeated on a lot of different animals,
including monkeys, which was very
controversial. And yes, while you can
transfer a tiny lab grown human brain
into a stroke induced monkey, more than
that has been done. This is actually one
of the big issues with organoids in
medicine and that is that there are so
many functional studies that have come
out. People don't know where to start.
Researchers have managed to transplant
stem cells where these kinds of trials
have failed in humans and there's a lot
of issues with that. Did they fail in
humans because something was not done
right? Did the researchers do something
else? Could it even be falsified? All of
these are important questions before we
even begin to look at people. Now, this
really is a very frustrating point for
me because I know people who are
suffering with conditions like
Parkinson's and ALS and treatments that
work in mice or monkeys could be a
lifesaver literally. But because of a
long history of things being done very
poorly to the tune of, I don't know,
plastic tracheas, there is a great
responsibility that researchers have to
make sure that a method is the best one
possible, that they do all of their due
diligence and consider every possible
side effect before putting them in
feeble. Aside from the ethics part of
that, at the very least, if something
goes terribly wrong, it could set the
field back a decade or more. With great
power comes great responsibility. We do
know that transplanting a human brain
organoid does end up taking root in the
brain and can even make projections all
the way into the spinal cord. But this
particular study from 2013 is why
intelligence is not usually studied in
chimera animals. And by chimeic I mean
having two different cell groups from
two different kinds of animals and in
this case human brain and other animal
brain. Human neurons are more dense and
tightly packed. They'll also interface
with other kinds of neurons if they're
just put there. Especially because brain
organoids are essentially fetal. they
adapt. However, the idea of endowing
animals with some kind of sentience that
they would not normally have is, yes,
not super ethical, and it doesn't seem
like there's a great deal of purpose.
So, a study that specifically looks at
intelligence is probably not going to
happen again. And that might be a
mistake because we might be ignoring
suffering that happens. And yes, there
are different ways to get human neurons
into a mouse. It can either be the brain
organoid route or you can take human
neural stem cells and inject them while
the mice is still developing and then
they will grow up with human neurons.
There's even been advancements in
getting human cells to compete more and
not being overtaken by other kinds of
cell types that is being used for
organs. Now, this one gets complicated
for other reasons. They gave mice
autism. It's important to note that
autism is a spectrum. It's actually many
conditions that all have some pretty
similar symptoms. Some forms of autism
seem very much to be genetic and other
forms can be induced. In this case, it's
an anti-convulsant medicine that causes
autism in young children if their parent
took it while pregnant. They took human
stem cells that have been exposed to the
anti-convulsant and then put them in a
developing mouse. Yes, the mice did show
what we would call autism in mice, which
involves social disturbances as well as
anxiety. More importantly, they were
able to definitively say what cell type
is causing it. When they turn them off,
it did ameliorate the mice's symptoms.
Now, this idea is really socially
complicated because autism is again a
spectrum. It can be very severe to
relatively mild and many people feel
that they do not need a cure and that is
fine too. If anything, this study just
helps us understand autism more. This
would not be a cure because these
neurons are specifically genetically
engineered to be able to be turned off
so that they could investigate the
symptoms.
It's complicated. Now, it's important to
note that there are no federal laws that
prevent people from cloning people, and
Congress has been trying to pass laws
for some time that would prohibit making
human animal chimeas for research. This
is why it's important to speak about
these things, frankly, and honestly,
yes, they're spooky, and I love the
spooky aspects of science, but these
technologies do have an awful lot of
good that they could do. They allow us
to study the human brain without
actually using a person. And brain
organoids are limited when they're not,
you know, in a body. We can actually see
the functional connections in the human
brain and an animal. But we should also
consider the potential suffering that
could be caused. It is a balancing act.
It's complicated. Now, I would ask, why
have we not cloned people yet? We've
cloned sheep. We clone mice all the
time. We can clone parts of people and
assemble them into body oids, taking
multiple organoids and putting them
together like Legos. So, why not people?
While there is no federal law, there is
a patchwork of laws that prevent various
uses in different states. While there is
that, I imagine if somebody really
wanted to make it happen and they had
the money to do it, they would. Many
clones seem to have chromosomal
abnormalities. We may see hundreds of
attempts and just get one clone out of
it. And that is usually what happens in
a lab. You can't really, you know, clone
your child 10 times and then just keep
the one that worked pretty okay. There's
a great deal of ethical concerns and
yeah, so you may be responsible for, I
don't know, nine clones of yourself that
are just a little off and then one
that's kind of okay, you can see the
problem here. Oh, and Minnesota does not
touch the issue of cloning for children.
Maybe you can, but you can't do it for
medical research. So, just to try to
answer the question, are brain organoids
actually cloned people? Not legally, not
yet. I could very easily see a world
where it became one. I was also really
disappointed that nobody talked about
brain organoids in the last presidential
debate because I definitely wanted to
see people yelling about baby brains in
robots and because people always ask
about my opinions on these things or try
to parse out my feelings based on my
reactions. My feelings are complicated.
Yes, I understand that these things have
the potential to maybe not be very
ethical. Part of me is just really wants
to see what happens when mad science
runs its course. But a much bigger part
of me acknowledges that this has the
possibility of doing a whole lot of good
and helping science as a whole. It will
save lives. It will develop treatments
that we never could have imagined before
because we didn't have access to a model
that worked. There's a big difference
between a mouse's brain and a human
brain. But you can make an intermediate
that kind of looks like ours. We do
collectively as humanity have a
responsibility to treat our lab animals
ethically. The reason I work with
microbes rather than mammals is because
I really don't have the heart for it. I
would be taking home my research
subjects. I can't do it. If you want to
hear more, you can check out these
articles and follow for